<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistics on Frederick Boehm&#39;s Professional Website</title>
    <link>/categories/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistics on Frederick Boehm&#39;s Professional Website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 21:51:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Generalized variance inflation factors</title>
      <link>/post/2017/12/06/generalized-variance-inflation-factors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 21:51:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/12/06/generalized-variance-inflation-factors/</guid>
      <description>Overview of the statistical model I am working with a linear mixed effects model,
\[vec(Y) = Xvec(B) + vec(G) + vec(E)\]
where \(Y\) is a n by 2 matrix of trait values with one row per subject and one column per trait, \(X\) is a 2n by 2f matrix containing genotypic data in two n by f blocks, both of which are one the diagonal (i.e., \(X\) is a block-diagonal matrix with two diagonal blocks), \(B\) is a f by 2 matrix of allele effect sizes, \(G\) is a n by 2 matrix of genotypic random effects, and \(E\) is a n by 2 matrix of random errors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Knott &amp; Haley (2000)</title>
      <link>/post/2017/11/19/thoughts-on-knott-haley-2000/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 00:33:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/11/19/thoughts-on-knott-haley-2000/</guid>
      <description>Overview I’ve been reading Knott and Haley (2000), an article that discusses methods for multivariate QTL mapping. I’m trying to pay special attention to their methods for testing the competing hypotheses of 1. close linkage and 2. pleiotropy for a pair of traits that map to a single genomic region.
 References Knott, Sara A, and Chris S Haley. 2000. “Multitrait Least Squares for Quantitative Trait Loci Detection.” Genetics 156 (2).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding REML for estimating variance components</title>
      <link>/post/2017/09/02/understanding-reml-for-estimating-variance-components/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 12:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/09/02/understanding-reml-for-estimating-variance-components/</guid>
      <description>Overview I used much of the summer of 2017 to study linear mixed effects models. I’m writing this blog post to document my experience. Perhaps readers will find it useful in designing their study plans for mixed models.
I found particularly useful Sections 8.4 and 8.5 of Wakefield (2013). The author describes in detail a general framework for linear mixed models before venturing into likelihood-based inference for these models. Particularly appealing to me, and differing from works of many others, is the emphasis of Wakefield (2013) on being explicit about conditioning.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>